Finding Aid for Lee Kefauver Papers 1970-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lee Kefauver Papers 1970-1985, 1972-1977
Kefauver, Lee, 1934-
1 linear feet
Feminist active in various civic and political causes and organizations, including the League of Women Voters, the Michigan Republican Party, and the Women's Equity Action League. Files relating to her work with different organizations and to her interest in political and women's rights issues.
00100 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was the gift of Lee Kefauver (Donor no. 8760 ) in July 1998. Additional accessions are expected.
The collection is open for research.
Lee Kefauver was born in Boston, Massachusetts and educated in Brookline where she lived for most of her youth. In 1958 she was transferred to Michigan where she met her future husband, Walter Ray Lavalli, who worked for Smith, Hinchman & Grylls Associates, a major Detroit architectural firm. Between 1968 and 1972 she attended classes in political science at Wayne State University in Detroit. Ms. Kefauver took an active interest in the political and social issues of her time, particularly those concerning equal rights for women and abortion rights. From 1968 until 1975 she was an active member of the Dearborn-Dearborn Heights chapter of the League of Women Voters, where she served as Publicity Chair and Chair of the Equal Rights Amendment, United States Congress, and Foreign Relations committees as well as serving on the board.
In 1970 she began working with the Michigan Organization for the Repeal of Abortion Laws, where she lobbied for bills before the Michigan legislature and worked with other pro-choice groups to influence legislation. Throughout her career Ms. Kefauver was active in a large number of formal and informal groups and coalitions working toward better living conditions for women. For a more complete account of her activities, refer to the documents in the Biographical/Personal folder. In 1971 Ms. Kefauver joined the Detroit chapter of the National Organization for Women (NOW). She served as chair of the Reproductive Rights Task Force of that chapter, and as NOW Michigan Coordinator for Reproductive Rights. In 1973 she was elected Michigan State Coordinator (President) of NOW, and served one eighteen month term. In 1976 Ms. Kefauver became active in the Women's Equity Action League (WEAL), representing them as a registered lobbyist, legislative coordinator, and as state president in 1979-1980. In 1978 she won the national WEAL Lobbying Award for the most effective contribution to lobbying on women's issues. As a member of the Feminist Bureau of Investigation, Ms. Kefauver compiled the Michigan Legislative Report in 1975 and 1976.
Ms. Kefauver was also an active member of the Republican Party, serving as a delegate to the State Convention several times and as a member of the Issues Committee. While her affiliation with the Republication Party may be surprising in light of her ardent feminism, she explained in a 1977 Delegate Questionnaire that: "I am originally from Boston, Mass. where the Republican party was the 'progressive' party, concerned about human rights and issues that affect people in their daily lives" (response dated February 1, 1977, Folder: Republican State Committee, State Conventions, 1974-1977). During this period, Ms. Kefauver became increasingly frustrated with the positions taken by the national and state Republican party. Her last act as a Republican was to join hundreds of other women in picketing the Republican National Convention held in Detroit.
In 1982 Ms. Kefauver moved to Massachusetts where she registered to vote as a Democrat and became involved in the Democratic Town Committees of the towns in which she has resided. For additional information, see the Biographical/Personal folder in Box 1.
One of Ms. Kefauver's children, her daughter Kari Lee Lavalli, also became involved in the struggle for equal rights when she filed a complaint with the Michigan Civil Rights Commission (MCRC) charging the "Dearborn Public Schools with discriminating against her by excluding her from shop classes, and forcing her to take homemaking classes instead" ("Teen Charges Bias in School," Detroit Free Press, March 13, 1974, 1-C, Folder: Public School "Desexigration" [Equal Access to Educational Facilities], 1973-1974).
The papers of Lee Kefauver document the local, state, and to some extent national activities and affiliations of a feminist activist during the turbulent 1970s. They reveal how groups of concerned organizations, both large and small, banded together to attempt to defeat anti-choice legislation and to defend the Equal Rights Amendment, and they illustrate some of the day to day business of these organizations. This collection contains information about small local organizations which may not be available elsewhere. The collection is divided into two main series, Organizations and Topical Files, which are preceded by a folder containing Biographical/Personal information.
Subjects:
Kefauver, Lee, 1934-; Feminists--Michigan.; League of Women Voters of Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.); Women's Equity Action League.; Women's rights--Michigan.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Vita, summaries of political activity, certificates, etc (Box 1)
- Organizations
  The Organizations series contains documents relating to political groups in which Ms. Kefauver was active or in which she had an interest. The Organizations series is arranged alphabetically. It includes information on groups such as the Feminist Bureau of Investigation, apparently a very small group which publicized Michigan politicians who had supported legislation favorable to women (in "Feminist Honor Roll" posters) and also awarded the "Keep-Em-Barefoot-&-Pregnant" Award to the politician who had sought to do the most harm to women through legislative action. Ms. Kefauver was particularly active in the League of Women Voters, both in the Dearborn Heights chapter and at the state level, and these documents reflect her involvement in the administration and activities of those organizations. In addition, she served on the League's Environmental Quality Commission and Foreign Relations Committee.
  Ms. Kefauver was also an active member of the Republican Party, serving as a delegate to the State Convention several times and as a member of the Issues Committee. The materials in these files reflect Ms. Kefauver's attempts to educate Michigan Republicans about the importance of women's issues, and so reflect the response (or lack thereof) of the Republican Party in Michigan to the emerging women's movement. However, the majority of the materials relating to the Republican State Committee demonstrate the routine kinds of communications between the party and its workers, and materials promoting specific candidates for state office. These documents make an interesting counterpoint with those reflecting Ms. Kefauver's participation in the Women's Equity Action League (WEAL). WEAL is "a nationwide women's rights organization founded in 1968 to promote greater economic progress on the part of American women, by investigating and seeking solutions to economic, educational, tax, and employment problems affecting women. WEAL lobbies and testifies on issues before Congress, writes legislation, and monitors the enforcement of laws, lawsuits, and federal regulations affecting women's rights" ("Position Description, Executive Director, Women's Equity Action League," December 1978, Folder: WEAL, National, 1978-1985). Ms. Kefauver served as State President of the Michigan chapter of WEAL and as such attended its national board meetings. She was also a registered lobbyist for WEAL and the "WEAL Michigan" folder contains extensive evidence of her communication with legislators and the press regarding legislation affecting women in Michigan.
  - Feminist Bureau of Investigation 1972-1982 (Box 1)
  - Feminist Women's City Club (Detroit) 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - League of Women Voters
    - Dearborn Heights Chapter 1970-1977 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Chapter 1971-1975 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Chapter, Environmental Quality Commission 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Chapter, Foreign Relations Committee 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Democratic Women's Caucus 1973-1982 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Women's Commission 1973-1980 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Women's Political Caucus 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Republican State Committee
    - Bylaws, Financial Statements, Reports, etc. 1971-1974 (Box 1)
    - Issues Committee 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Materials from Leadership Conference August 1975 (Box 1)
    - State Conventions 1974-1977 (Box 1)
  - Women's Equity Action League (WEAL)
    - Michigan Division 1973-1980 (Box 1)
    - National Organization 1978-1985 (Box 1)
  - Women's Groups Addresses 1976-1982 (Box 1)
  - Women's Liberation Coalition of Michigan (undated) (Box 1)
  - Women Organized to Meet Existing Needs (WOMEN) 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Women's Republican Caucus 1975 (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series contains information on specific political and legislative issues, particularly subjects relating to abortion rights and women's health. The Topical Files series is arranged alphabetically, and contains correspondence, reports, newspaper clippings, and pamphlets dating from 1970 to 1980 relating to issues and activities with which Ms. Kefauver was involved or in which she had an interest.
  - Abortion: Michigan Women's Abortion Suit 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - August 26th Celebrations and Actions 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Battered Spouses Bills 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Congresswoman Martha Griffith's Testimony on Women's Issues 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  - Feminist Women's Health Centers (Detroit) 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Civil Rights Commission 1971-1975 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Legislative Reports 1971-1975 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Public Health Code Revisions 1974-1977 (Box 1)
  - Public School "Desexigration" (Gender Desegregation of Educational Facilities) in Michigan 1973-1974 (Box 1)